<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise vvriten by Iohan Valerian a greatte clerke of Italie, which is intitled in latin Pro sacerdotum barbis translated in to Englysshe</title>
            <title>Pro sacerdotum barbis. English</title>
            <author>Valeriano, Pierio, 1477-1560.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1533</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 122:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise vvriten by Iohan Valerian a greatte clerke of Italie, which is intitled in latin Pro sacerdotum barbis translated in to Englysshe</title>
                  <title>Pro sacerdotum barbis. English</title>
                  <author>Valeriano, Pierio, 1477-1560.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 [i.e. 31], [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Tho. Bertheleti,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.XXXIII. [1533]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Pro sacerdotum barbis.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Leaf 31 misnumbered 30.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Beards --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE VVRITEN BY IOHAN</hi> Valerian a greatte clerke of <hi>ITALIE,</hi> which is intitled in latin <hi>Pro Sacerdotum barbis</hi> tranſlated in to Englyſſhe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:10933:2"/>
            <head>¶The preface of the tranſlatour to the reder.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen, gentyll reder, that here in Englande hath bene dyuers tymes bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes for werynge of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſo that (as it appereth) in no realme they haue bene leſſe accepted. Alſo we maye perceyue, that in Italie, all thoughe theyr vſe varye farre from ours (for ſhauynge is as lyttell vſed there as beardes be here) yet hath there ben greatte variance for the ſame cauſe, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the clergie. Whervpon a lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that countrey, called Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pierius Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, wrote a piſtell to the Cardinall Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the defence of prieſtis beardes: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue tranſlated into oure Englyſſhe tonge, partly for the cauſe afore named, and partely bicauſe I haue euer vſed to weare a bearde, and haue ben many tymes challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and rebuked for the ſame. And here it is to be noted, that if it be proued no vnmete thynge for a prieſte to weare a bearde, who ſhuld both in apparell and dedes ſhewe a ſad and an honeſte example, it may ſeme ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the more ſufferable in a laye manne. But
<pb facs="tcp:10933:3"/> peraduenture I myght be iudged of ſomme men to be a very preſumptuous perſone, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that I hauynge but lyttelle lernynge, wolde take vppon me to tranſlate. Howe be it, whan I ſawe it was no great weighty matter, it made me ſo moche the more bolde to procede, in folowynge myn intent.</p>
            <p>Furthermore where as I haue founde my copy in many places very tedious, by plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes of wordes, I haue in my tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vſed a ſhorter way, gatheryng to gether the effecte of the matter, as I thought moſt mete for my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>More ouer yf I haue in any place varyed farre from the true menyng of the ſentence: I do ſubmytte my ſelfe to them that be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lerned, deſyryng them to holde me excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to accompt it as an vnlerned mannes acte. But ſhortly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, yf thoſe that ſhall rede this lytell boke, do wey the matter indifferentely, I truſte they ſhall fynde it proued by good reaſon, that berdes ar nat ſo gretly to be diſpreiſed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be vſed &amp; worne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10933:3"/>
            <head>¶Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pierius Valerian to the moſt reuerende father, the Cardinall Medices.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or bycauſe moſte reuerende father, there be dyuers, not of ſmall auctoritie, goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to tempt the pope (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng no regard to his ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, wherewith he is nowe greuouſly vexed) to bryng vp ageyne a lawe of a certayne counſeyle concernyng beardes, ſtrengthed and renewed (as they ſay) by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander the thyrd, whiche before our tyme a fewe yeres, hathe bene kepte, and by our dayes, I thynke worthyly lefte. Therfore ye haue warned vs all, that lyue vnder your dominion, to begynne to ſhaue our beardes, before this commaundement be put forthe: and ſo we ſhall bothe be exaumple to other, and alſo do that wyllyngely, that elles we ſhulde be compelled to doo by a lawe. The whiche thynge we are redye to obeye, onely moued by your auctoritie and iudgemente, without conſtraynynge of any lawe. Howe be it there be many wyſe, counnynge, ye and alſo vertuous men, that allowe nat greatly this matter, and thynke by this meanes the
<pb facs="tcp:10933:4"/> ſhaue their beardes for humilitie in diſpyſing of apparell, that they myght be diſfigured, and hadde in deriſion amonge the people, the whiche peraduenture we graunt in ſhearynge of the heare aboue the eares: but there is not one man, that dothe well conſyder, woll iudge humilitie in takynge ſo moche care for ſmothenes of the mouthe. For truly ſhauyng of the chynne and all the face, beganne of a wycked and a delycate mynde: and they that often vſe it, are iuged without doubte, to be of the feminine ſorte, though they haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other good qualities and excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. I myght reherſe here for my purpoſe exaumples innumerable of all the aunciente men, bothe of grekes and hebrewes: but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we be Romayns, and it is the Romaine churche, that we are nowe in hande withal, it ſhall nat varie farre from our matter, yf before we ſpeake of thynges doone in oure tyme, we fyrſt reherſe the dedes of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers. Wherfore nowe lette vs ſee, howe the Romayns in tyme paſt eſtemed beardes. They truely lyke manly menne, were longe ere they wold ſuffre any barbours amongeſt theym, and for that cauſe the auncientis of them amonge wryters were called for the moſte parte, the vnſhauen men.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10933:4"/>
            <p>☞ Of truthe the .544. yere after the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of Rome, the vſe of barbours was founde: &amp; them P. Ticinius Mena brought out of Sicilia, if we mowe beleue <hi>Varro:</hi> And Plini alſo beareth wytnes, before that tyme they lyued vnſhauen, and fyrſte of all men, Aphricanus vſed to be ſhauen dayely: whom Auguſtus Octauianus folowed very diligently. And truely Scipio was euer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ſofte and a feminate felow, ſo that his delycate facion and ſtrange apparell, neyther after the maner of the Romaynes, nor yet ware lyke, and alſo his great ſlouthe, is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of to this daye: In ſo moch that in that ſame buſynes, whiche was of greatte and as weighty as euer the Romaynes had any, I meane when they wente aboute to diſtroye Carthage, for the reſtorynge of the libertie of Italie, and ſafegarde of them ſelfe, and the honour of theyr name: he was complei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of euen in the towne of Rome, nat priue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye but openly in the Senate howſe, bycauſe whyles he ruled, the exercyſyng of the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of warre were forſlowed.</p>
            <p>Therfore I ſay, go ye to, folow ye the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of the Sicilians, folow ye aſſo the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge apparelle, the delicacie and prodigalytie of the Syracuſans, dampned by the manyfolde
<pb facs="tcp:10933:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> prouerbes of auncient men, and admytte ye be not daſtardes and cowardes, but ſtronge, excellent, and triumphant, yet by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ye minyſſhe a great parte of your glory. But what ſhall I ſpeke now of Auguſtus? he without doubte was neuer ſo moche ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be of a femynate mynde, by the baudy verſis that he wrote in the baynes, as by the often vſe of ſhauyng.</p>
            <p>But leeſt I ſhulde bryng in many examples in ſo euident a matter, in concluſion, all put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge away of heare hath ben eſtemed, at al tymes, and by the conſent of all people, to be as it were a certayne wo manny ſhe thyng. By that it came vppe, that certayne nations wold ſhaue theyr beardes whan they mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (in the token of ſorowe) that they might bewayle theyr wretchednes with a woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe facion, bycauſe they thought, it agreed not to mourne with a manlye bearde.</p>
            <p>And truly the Romains did eſteme their ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis of ſo gret honor, that they wold neuer pic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture Iupiter, their god, without a bearde.</p>
            <p>Of how moch auctoritie &amp; grauitie berdes cauſid the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis of the toun of Rome to be it apperith plainly bi this that folowith: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome was taken of the Senons, &amp; their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were entred, euery one of the faders ſit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10933:5"/> at his doore, with that beardly dignitie, brought their ennemies (al though they were right cruell) in ſuche admiration, that they thoughte euery citizen, that they ſawe ſo ſyt, had bene a god. Tylle at the laſte one, that was ſomewhat bolder than the other, began to ſtroke one of the ſenatours beardes: and he wolde nat ſuffre hym, but ſtrake hym with a rodde. For the whiche dede theyr cruel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies being wroth, ſlewe al thoſe ancient &amp; honorable Romaynes, not leauynge one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue. Thus ye maye ſee, that they that the Romaynes ſworde coude nat tame, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed by the reuerence of their berdes: And ageyne thoſe Romayns rather choſe to loſe theyr lyues with theyr berdes, than to haue the maieſtie of theyr mouthe defiled. Yet I wol not deny, but certayn people, ye &amp; alſo of the noble ſort, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the berd to be ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſuffred the heer of the heed to grow lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hind: the which thing they ſay, the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s did. And Homer writeth, that the Abba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes firſt diuiſed it: &amp; for the ſame cauſe (Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux ſaith) they were callid Euboia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with the long heer behind. Alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Timeus deſcriuid Hector, he preiſed his goodly lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge heer, han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng down at his back: But that thing made the Lacedemonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnlike all other nations:
<pb facs="tcp:10933:6"/> And alſo manye other fonde thynges were brought vppe by the ſame, farre frome the cuſtom of other kyndes of people. The cauſe why that they commanded beardes to be ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and to nouryſſhe the heer longe behynd, was to the intente that they myghte be the more ſafe in batayle, bycauſe theyr ennemies ſhulde haue none aduantage, in takyng holde by theyr chynnes. More ouer if they dydde purpoſe to fle, they ſhuld remembre a longe boundell of heare to hange downe behynde at theyr backes, wherby theyr enmies might take theyr handes ful, and draw them backe ageyne: and ſo for feare of that, they ſhuld not intende to flee, but lyke men without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope of remedy, boldly reſiſt and aſſayle their ennemies. But when this conſtitution, and thoſe that ruled in that tyme, were ones worne out and forgotten, it was neuer more after vſed.</p>
            <p>But nowe to procede to ſuche thynges, as apperteyne to oure matter, I wolde verye fayne, that thoſe delycate felowes our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, whiche are ſo extreme ageynſte vs, bycauſe they thynke it ſoo moche vnſemely, that a prieſte ſhulde weare a bearde: ſhulde declare to me, what fylthynes is in a berde. For truely I can fynde in it nothynge filthy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10933:6"/> nor diſhoneſt. But to the end it may the more playnly appere, lette vs fyrſt declare what a beard is: and ſo parauenture if there be any thynge in it amys, we ſhal perceyue it. There be many thynges, whiche are hydden in the begynnynge, that by the definition ſhall be more openly knowen.</p>
            <p>The bearde is a garment for manly chekes gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nature for comlynes &amp; for helthe:<note place="margin">The de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bearde.</note> &amp; therfore the latines named it a garment, and thoſe that were ſhauen, they counted them as naked and vncladde. And alſo ye ſhal fynde wrytten in manye auctours theſe wordes: Theyr chekes were cladde with yonge wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare. That a bearde is a token of manly nature, the thynge ſelfe dothe ſhewe more playne, than any man can declare.</p>
            <p>Diogines, whiche deſpiſed all ſhauen fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, dyd not without a cauſe make this aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to a barbour: that he ware his beard, to the intent he myghte euer haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, that he was a man. And yet to this daye, all the nations of the Eaſte parties, where ſo euer they ſe men with ſuche ſmothe faces, they calle them women in ſcorne.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is had in remembrance, how Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander of Macedone, a prince of great name, was ſcorned bothe of his ſubiectes and men
<pb facs="tcp:10933:7"/> of warre, ye and alſo of all nations, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wolde be ſhauen, to ſhewe hym ſelfe feminine: And Atheneus dothe wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Chriſippus, that he was the auctour of ſhauynge.</p>
            <p>It is openly knowen amongeſt all kyndes of men, that chyldren, women, gelded men, &amp; thoſe that are tender and delycat, are euer ſene withoute beardis: and therby it may be eaſily vnderſtande, to whome thoſe that are ſhauen, may be lykened. But leſte we ſhulde tarie to longe in ſo euident a matter, lette vs paſſe forth to other thynges, whiche we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ethe a bearde.</note>That the berde is gyuen of nature for com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, we may ꝓue by this. Where as nature hath garnyſhed trees with bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches &amp; leues: likeſwiſe to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the more i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>creſing of their dignitie, ſhe hath apparelled them with heer: in ſo moche that the poetis put no difference, but plainly affirme, that men ar as moch diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>figured, whan theyr beardis be ſhauen, as trees be, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their leues be falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>It was nat for naught, that Haliab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, with many other excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t philoſophers did write, that the berde of a man was giuen of nature for comelynes &amp; dignitie. And for that cauſe thou ſhalt fynd, that euery one of them, if he
<pb facs="tcp:10933:7"/> were but lyttell bearded, eyther on the ouer lyp onely, or els vpon the verye toppe of his chynne, as often as he behelde hym ſelfe in a glaſſe, or put his hand to his mouth, he wold put great faute in nature, and bewayle hym ſelfe, for beinge ſo made. For like as peerles are eſtemed the more precious for their gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, euen ſo of the greatnes a bearde taketh his preyſe.</p>
            <p>Artemidorus ſaythe, that the fathers are worthy to be honored, whan their chyldren be ſene with manly beardes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it is worthye oure labour, to here the opinion of Lucian, whiche thought it as moche vnnatural to ſhaue a mans beerd, as if thou ſhuldeſt go aboute to ſhere a lyons maane.</p>
            <p>Theſeus the diſciple of Hercules, whiche atte that tyme was mooſte excellente in ſtrengthe, wolde neuer ſhaue his bearde, to the intent he myght profeſſe his valyantnes by that ſame mannely ſtate. And for that cauſe ſome men ſaye, he made a lawe, that yonge men ſhulde ſhaue theyr fyrſt beardes, and offre theym to the goddes, as a deere and thankefulle gyfte, thynkynge that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge myghte be offerred more meeter for that age: and alſo he wolde dedicate that,
<pb facs="tcp:10933:8"/> as the fyrſte fruites, to the flodes, &amp; to the god Apollo, accordynge to the ſuperſtition of thoſe dayes. But this is nothynge to our purpoſe. But Plinie the yonger, in his tyme dydde very moche preyſe Euphrates, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente Philoſopher, the whiche opteyned moche honour by his great and white beard. For beardes were ſo moch honoured in olde tyme, that a philoſopher without a bearde, was very lytell eſtemed. More ouer he that had a bearde, excepte his lyuynge were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued in grauitie of maners, he was yuell reported amonge the people, bycauſe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable bearde and his habite was in ſyghte, and the philopher appered nat. In ſo moche that the moſte aunciente and diſcrete men in thoſe dayes wolde iudge bothe wyſedome and good maners to be ioyned with a beard.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lth that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſeth.</note>Furthermore as concernyng the helth that cometh by a bearde, we may proue by this, that for nouryſhynge of hym ſelfe, it ſucketh out the abundant &amp; groſſe humours from the chekes, and by that meanes it preſerueth the feethe longe frome peryſhynge: whiche doth not lyghtely happen to thoſe that are often ſhauen. For they (for the mooſte parte) are other totheles longe before theyr tyme, or els they haue very moche peyne of the tothe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10933:8"/> ache. More ouer in the hotte ſommer it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth the face from the burnynge and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of the ſonne beames: and in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it bereth of the colde ſtormes and ſharpe blaſtis of the wynd: and it ſaueth a man from the quinſie, the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me piles, &amp; many other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. And to the intent we ſhulde gyue the more credence to theſe thynges, it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fablyng philoſophers, that Aſculapius did alway weare a berd, whan his father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym, was euer ſhauen. Than it is to be thought, that he, the whiche was called the auctour of helth, wold folow ſuch thingis as perteined to helth. Therfore ſeinge there be ſo many good qualities in a bearde, I ſee no ſuche fylthynes nor viciouſnes in it, for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it ſhulde be lothed. Welle than, if ſuche thyngis, whiche are honourable, whiche are profytable and helthefull, and whiche are of any eſtimation at all, ſhall be iudged vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy for a prieſt, I thynke it wol be harde for vs to fynde what thyng ſhal be mete for the prieſtly ſtate. But whether ſhall I call theſe deſpiſers of beardes vnequall or malicious, whiche are ſo enuiouſly ſette ageynſt vs, that all our worſhyppinges, all our prayers, all our offrynges, which we miniſtre to god im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, in concluſion all that euer we do, be
<pb facs="tcp:10933:9"/> hit neuer ſo pure and chaſte, is vnſauerye to them, onely by the meanes of our beardes. And they allowe no prieſtis, but thoſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ageynſte the ſentences of moſt ſobre and wyſe men, cutte away the worſhyp of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode. In ſo moche that if any man deny to ſhaue his bearde: by and by they woll ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende hym, and deſpyſe hym lyke one that had forſaken his feyth. For truly they think where a bearde is, there can be no goodnes, no holynes, nor no perfecte religion. And fyrſte of all they ley ageynſte vs, the power of the lawes, cryenge oute that all thynge ſhall fall to miſchefe, if we ſay, that the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes are nat to be obeyed. But without doute they knowe full well, howe moch we eſteme the lawes. Therfore they are ſo moche the bolder, bycauſe we haue euer gladly gyuen place to ſuche argumentes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">oure ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er lawis</note>Yet fyrſt let them tel me, whether they wyl allege for them the lawes of nature, or the lawes written, or the lawes taken by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumples of holye menne, or elles the lawes ordeyned by the inſpiration of the holy goſt. I fynde that theſe foure haue bene kyndes of laudable lyuynge, euery one in his tyme: wherby that menne mighte haue ledde their lyues, in as moche as perteynethe to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10933:9"/> thynges, frome the begynnynge of the worlde hytherto, bothe with laude and preyſe to them ſelfe, and ſaluation of their ſoules. Then if they woll allege the lawes of nature, that men ſhall ſhaue theyr bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the thynge it ſelfe woll repugne ageinſt them: ye and alſo both wyſe men and foles, as many as are nowe, or as euer haue bene ſyns any man could remembre, can tel them, that Nature hath made women with ſmothe facis, and men rough and full of heere. And more ouer it hathe bene euer a monſtruous thynge, to ſe a woman with a beard, though it were verye lyttell, as the Grekes ſtoryes ſhewen of the woman byſſhoppe, whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the Pedaſenſes was chiefe ruler in the ſacrifice of Minerua. Therfore who ſo euer, by any crafte or buſynes, gothe aboute to make a man beardles, it may be leyde to his charge, that he hath done ageynſt the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of Nature.</p>
            <p>¶To this they wolle make aunſwere, that Nature hathe made many thynges, whiche were but of ſmalle effecte, tylle after by mannes wytte they were broughte to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pourpoſe, as the fruites of the erthe onely for meate, and water for drynke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ordeyned: wherof mans wyt hath
<pb facs="tcp:10933:10"/> diuiſed to make both breadde and wyne, with many other delycates.</p>
            <p>Alſo nature hath ſette all placis as a wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, full of ſharpe thornes, buſſhes, and great trees, where ſoone after the inuentiue wyttes of men haue diuiſed to make gay gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dens, goodly earable feldes, fayre medowes and orchardes. And lyke as many thynges haue ben brought to a better order by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, by the perſwaſyons, by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, and by the experience of wyſe men: euen ſo it was ordeyned, that beardes ſhulde be ſhauen to putte awaye the diſcommoditie.</p>
            <p>But me thynketh, that thoſe delicate law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers myght well be lykened to the Sybary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, the whiche in lyke maner diſtroyed all the cockes in theyr countrey, leſt with theyr importunate crowyng before day, they ſhuld be diſeaſed in theyr ſwete mornynge ſlepes. But yet this gothe well, that the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is on our ſyde, whiche they can nat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: and yet theyr wyttes are ſo frowarde, that ſtyll they brynge forth ſuche tryfils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt it. Therfore they lette paſſe the lawe of nature, and flee to a lawe wrytten for the commoditie of a fewe perſones, in whoſe helpe they putte all theyr hope of victorye. But there be thre maner of lawes wrytten.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10933:10"/> The fyrſte is the lawe of Moyſes,<note place="margin">Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten.</note> durynge vnto the comminge of Chriſte: The ſeconde is that, whiche we haue taken to folowe by the exaumple of Chriſte: or elles inſtitute, by auctoritie of the appoſtels. The thyrde is the Decrees made by the power of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes and counſels.</p>
            <p>But bycauſe we beganne with the lawe of Moyſes, let vs fyrſt ſe, whether ſhauynge be commanded there or not. Verily if ye lyſt to marke the maners of the Hebrewes, ye ſhall rede in the hiſtory of kyngis,<note place="margin">2. Re. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne meſſangers were ſente from Dauid to kynge Hannon to comforte hym for the deth of his father, the whiche meſſangers, this barbarous kynge ſuſpectynge, ſente theym ageyne with theyr faces halfe ſhauen, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyte and ſcorne of theyr prince. Wherfore Dauid commaunded them to remayne in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico, tyll their beardes were growen agein, leſt that fylthy ſyght ſhulde be ſhewed to the people. The whiche thynge he wolde not haue done, if ſhauynge had ben vſed at that tyme: for then they might haue ſhauen the reſte of theyr faces, and all had bene well. In lyke wiſe if we ſerche the lawes of them, we ſhall fynde ſhauynge forbydden in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui. 19.</note>Alſo it is forbydden in the Leuiticall bokes to all people in generalle, and ſpeciallye to the prieſtis it is a commaundement withoute anye exception, that they ſhall not ſhaue theyr beardes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aie. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</note>Furthermore amonge other miſeries, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che god thretnethe to the Moabitis, by the wordes of the prophete Eſaie, well nere in euery chapiter he ſaythe: Theyr beardes ſhall be cutte awey. Here ye maye ſee, howe moche this token of a womannyſhe mynd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, was hated amonge them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 132.</note>It is not for nought, that the honourable memorie of Aarons bearde is ſongen dayly in our temples before the aulters of god and his ſainctis: in ſo moche that the oyntment, wherwith his bearde was annoynted, is had in remembraunce.</p>
            <p>More ouer the people of Nazareth, thoſe mooſte holy menne, whiche were dedicate to god, dydde lette growe theyr buſſhes and beardes, in token of holynes: And for that cauſe we rede, that ſayncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptyſte, the meſſanger of Chriſte, wolde neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre the heare of his heed nor bearde to be cutte.</p>
            <p>And by what argument more playne, maye we proue beardes to pleaſe God, than by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10933:11"/> this, that the fathers, when they could haue no chylderne, they made vowes to let theyr beardes growe? The whiche thyng if thoſe fathers had thoughte vnthankefull to god, doubteles they wolde not haue hoped to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne any grace of hym by ſuche vowes. They without doubte beinge warned of the offence, that perauenture certayne delycate felowes commytted by ſhauynge of theyr beardes, dydde intende bothe to mende the erroure, and alſo to gette ageyne the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of God, by the meanes of that vowe.</p>
            <p>Trewely ye ſhall fynde amonge the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, dyuers tymes beardes ſhauen, where any vnſufferable peyne, or gret wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes dyd happen to them, to the intente they myght ſhewe them ſelfe as men ſpoyled of all theyr welthe. A hole daye, ye a hole yere wolde not ſerue me, yf I ſhuld continue after this maner, to remembre all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and exaumples written in thoſe dayes, where beardes are commended: the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynge ſeinge it is ſo playne, I thynke it not mete to conſume any longer tyme in a mattier ſoo openlye knowen. It appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe in the olde lawe, that beardes were not forbydden, but ordeyned to be worne,
<pb facs="tcp:10933:12"/> and commaunded by God hym ſelfe, not to be putte awaye.</p>
            <p>Nowe go to, let vs come to an other lawe, whiche oure chriſten religion hathe folowed. 1529. yere. This lawe is named by our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines the lawe of grace, whiche we deuide into the lawe of examples, &amp; the lawe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the inſpiration of the holye ghooſte. The lawe of examples is of ſo great aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that that alone ſuffiſeth, as it apperith by the wordes of Chriſt, whan he hym ſelfe profeſſed to gyue exaumple to vs. Therfore we are euer wonte to putte Chriſte afore vs for an example. And by that argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Igna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius, the diſciple of ſayncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſte, was moued ageynſt the ſuperſticiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of certayne menne, whiche thought them ſelfe the holyer, bycauſe they abſteyned euer from fleſſhe. Chriſte (ſayth he) dydde eate fleſſhe, Peter dyd eate fleſhe, and thoſe that folowed after: wherfore ſhuld we than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of holynes take awey the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge therof. Chriſt hath gyuen vs example, that what ſo euer he hath done, we ſhulde do the ſame, as farre as our power doth exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And ſo we may playnly ſaye, that euery acte of Chriſte our auctour, is a lawe and forme of our lyuynge. And this beinge graunted, I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10933:12"/> wolde wytte of our accuſers, whether they haue any commaundement, ſayeng, or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſte, wherby he dothe eyther com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, or ſhewe, or at the leeſt weye agree, that mens beardes ſhuld be ſhauen. Without doubte there is none founde of that maner. On the other parte the exaumple of Chriſte hym ſelfe, whiche is ſayde euer to weare a bearde: and the maners of Peter &amp; Paule, and all the appoſtels, may be iudged a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient defence for beardes. And there be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn men, which ſo deſcriue the face of Chriſt by knowlege of their fore fathers, that they affirme, he had a longe and a yelowe berde: neyther he is none otherwyſe peynted nor caruen of the grekes, the latines, nor none other nations, as it is openly knowen. Peter to whom chiefely was gyuen by Chriſte the auctoritie of our chriſten feythe, we picture hym in our temples euer with a bearde, both in braſſe, in marbull, and with colours. Nor we ſe no man pictured with a greater berde, than Paule, whiche was a maiſter of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge: to whoſe moſte wyſe inſtructions we are euer obedient. Andrewe, Thomas, and all the felowſhyppe of them, are gloriouſly ſette forth with great beardes.</p>
            <p>To this they woll make anſwere, that it is
<pb facs="tcp:10933:13"/> but a lyght argument, to diuine by pictures, what maner of face Chriſte and his apoſtils had, ſeinge it hath euer ben graunted to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etis and peynters to feyne what they lyſte. Well lette vs graunte to that, yet neuer the leſſe ye can not denye, but it is the generalle agreemente of all menne, that Chriſte hym ſelfe and his apoſtels, whiche are the chiefe auctours of our prieſtis, ſhalbe peynted &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen with beardes: by the whiche common conſente it maye eaſily be perceyued, that a bearde hath ſome good propretie perteyning to holynes, and doth brynge preyſe to euery holy man.</p>
            <p>The gentyles vſed a cuſtome, to ſhewe by the habyte of theyr goddis, what thynges they eſtemed moſte precious amongeſt them. And for this cauſe the Lacedemonians dydde not onely picture Mars lyke a manne of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, but alſo for the moſte parte all other goddis and goddeſſis: for bycauſe they eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nothynge more precious than armour, thei thought it behoued the goddis to be gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhed with armour.</p>
            <p>The Phenices, whiche were only gyuen to marchandiſe, dydde appareyle theyr goddis with purſis full of money: bycauſe they iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him moſt bleſſed, that had moſt money.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10933:13"/> So in lyke maner bicauſe we thynk nothing more honorable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a berd, we iuge it beſt to picture our god, &amp; his diſciples with beardis.</p>
            <p>Verily we can nat proue, that euer ſayncte Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the meſſanger of Chriſte, was ſhauen, nor yet ſayncte Iames, who amongeſt other good gyftes of a vertuous mynd was great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preyſed for this, that he wolde neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre hym ſelfe to be ſhauen. And ſhall we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy people, blame in any man, or forbyd vnder peyne of curſynge, that thynge, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was by the allowance of all people ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred in thoſe holy men, taught by Chriſt our ſauiour, and very ſonne of god, and rekened amonge the warkes of vertue, as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a perfecte and a moderate lyfe? But nowe of late, we haue not onely lefte the name of good maners, but alſo the veri right patheway of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Iamis, whiche opteyned his name by the continuall kepynge of Iuſtyce, was moche preyſed, bycauſe he neuer vſed ſhauynge nor annoyntyng, nother yet waſhyng in baynes. &amp;c. And ſhal we ſclander them as yuel peple, which deſpiſe ſhauing, &amp; ſuche other fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites? Thus if our lord god ware a beerd in token of manhod, if Peter, if Paule, &amp; al the apoſtels dyd the ſame, &amp; finally if there be no ther ſayeng nor monition fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:10933:14"/> auctours of our feythe ageynſte beardes: for what cauſe then ſhulde we regarde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnynge of beardes by any lawe, or feare the thretnynges of any man, ſeing god is on oure ſyde, whoſe ſonne we folowe in that habyte?</p>
            <p>The fourthe parte of our matter is, that we ſhall ſerche, whether this diſanullyng of beardis be commended or not in the thyrde kynde of written lawes, whiche were made by the inſpiration of the holy goſte.</p>
            <p>Of truthe the gides of our vertuous lyuing, called holy men, haue ordeyned ſome conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, withoute any mencion made before of god or his diſciples, or any example ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, but onely ſtyred vp (as they ſaye) by that ſame godly inſpiration, the whiche thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges nede nat here to be reherſed. Of this ſorte are the decrees of the counſels, I mene thoſe, whiche we are bounde to beleue. For I beleue this, that a generall counſell truely gethered, determyneth nothynge concernyng our feyth, without the inſpiration of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſte, and them we ought alway to allow and firmely beleue. But the lawe of maners and cuſtomes, varienge ofte tymes by the meanes of the place, tyme, or condicions of the perſons, ſauer more humayn tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godly:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10933:14"/> yet our accuſers prepared of theſe wepons, taken out of olde vulgar bokes, and putte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt our armie the counſell of Carthage, vnder whoſe helpe and defence, they make warre ageynſte beardes, deſpiſynge theym, and thretnynge theyr vtter diſtruction: like as though the diſtroyeng of that ſame beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull warke of nature, were done by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the holy gooſte: and as though he, whiche in tyme paſte dydde not without a cauſe ſhewe hym ſelfe mercyfull to thoſe, that made vowes to let their beardes grow, ſhulde nowe be ageynſt hym ſelfe in the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelle of Carthage, and begynne to deſpyſe beardes. The whiche thynges truely howe vnworthy they are to be counted the actis of god, the moſte innocent chylde in the worlde may perceyue: yet thoſe felowes are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to make god the auctour of ſuche ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iecte and fylthye buſyneſſes. But thoughe theyr feblenes of brayne ought to be forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, bycauſe they can not frame theyr wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to conceyue hygher thynges: yet it is wyſedom to take hede, leſt vnder the colour of goodnes, they ſhulde deceyue other men. Therfore nowe lette vs here what law they allege for them, and that is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clerici ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> comam nutriant, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> barba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10933:15"/> Clerkes ſhall neyther lette grow theyr buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes nor beardes. They ſey, this lawe was fyrſte made by the counſell of Carthage, and renewed by Alexander the thyrde, &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed by many of later tyme: &amp; that it ought not to be deſpiſed of vs. As though we were ſuche maner of people, that we wold inforce ſome thynge ageynſte the lawes: or els that we dyd not vnderſtande, if men ſhulde begyn to deſpyſe the lawes, that ſoone after euery thynge wolde be brought out of frame: and than ſhulde we ſee holy and vnholy thynges mixt to gether, nothing holy, nothing honeſt, nor nothing laudably done. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes are ones broken, the recourſe of marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſe betwene citie &amp; citie ſhalbe loſt, the leege of the people ſhall not be kepte, no good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall be regarded, no reaſon, no Iuſtyce, nor no ryghte ſhall remayne. It ſhoulde be leful than for euery man to leade his life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne luſte: than ſhulde we ſee ſuche trouble amonge all ſortis of people, that we ſhuld be conſtreyned to hyde vs in the wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, to crepe in to dennes and deſerte places of the erthe, to be kepte ſafe from the inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of them that are of greatter power. Wherfore I thynk that a law made, allowed of the reulers, and ſtrengthed by the vſe of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10933:15"/> the people, ought to be kept of al men. What ſhall we do therfore in this caſe? There is a lawe layde ageynſt all our reſons, our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is at a poynte, we are ouercomen, we are ſhatered abrode, and put to flyght, the ſectis of delycate perſons beare all the rule, &amp; they bynde vs to trifelynge maners. The ſobre and erneſt facion of the Romaynes is decaid, we muſt nowe waxe wanton by a newe law, we muſte be ſhauen, there may no heer grow on our facis, and to ſpeke one worde for all, ye and that a newe worde, we muſte become womanlyke. This is euen the very thynge, that our accuſers haue choſen onely for the defence of their delycatenes. With this they ſtryue ageynſt vs, with this they wounde vs euerychone, with this thynge alone, they thynke to diſtroye vs: So that except men of holy orders haue ſmothe and ſhynyng fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, they ſhall be pulled away from the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, they ſhall be putte out of the churches, there ſhall be no place, where people reſort, lefte free for them to abyde in. But we haue to longe kepte ſilence.</p>
            <p>Therfore nowe go to, lette vs bryng forth oure armye agaynſte theym, and fyrſte of alle, lette vs wynde awaye frome theym that ſame ingyn that is the chiefe grounde
<pb facs="tcp:10933:16"/> of our warre, &amp; therby we ſhal ouerthrowe all theyr holle power.</p>
            <p>I denye it playnly, I ſay it is not made in the counſaile of Carthage. For we may light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly proue, that certayne yeres afore tyme, for lacke of a true copie, theyr bokes were falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly printed, and this worde <hi>radant,</hi> ſhauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye: whiche chaungeth the holle ſentence, For the mooſte ancient, moſte holy, and moſt wyſeſt men do agree, that it is redde in Gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cian after this maner. <hi>Clerici ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> comam nutriant, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> barbam radant,</hi> Clerkes ſhal nother lette growe their buſſhes, nor ſhaue theyr beardes. There is no man can denye, but theſe wordes are wrytten of the counſel of Carthage. It was happye, that this ſame ſtorye of counſels was of late brought to lyght: wherin without doubt the counſell of Carthage dothe agree in this ſentence, with the olde wrytten bokes, whiche are in the librarie of Palatine: and there of truthe we fynde it wrytten thus: <hi>Clericus nec co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam nutriat, nec barbam radat,</hi> A clerke ſhall nother lette grow his buſſhe, nor ſhaue his beard.</p>
            <p>At this our ennemyes waxe pale, therfore let vs ſtycke to it lyke men we ſhall ſet vpon them with an other wyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whiche ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreyne
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10933:16"/> them to gyue ouer incontinent.</p>
            <p>They allege theſe wordes folowynge, to be redde in a piſtil of Alexander the thyrde, written to the archbyſſhoppe of Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. <hi>Clerici qui comam et barbam nutriunt, etiam inuiti a ſuis archidiaconis tondiantur,</hi> Clerkes that lette growe theyr buſſhes and beardes, ſhall be ſhorne of theyr archedea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, whether they wyl or not. But lyke as in the ſentence before, ſome vncleane ſhauer hath ſhauen away a worde, ſo by lyke, here in this piſtyll of Alexander, ſome brayneles felowe hath added to a word. For by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grement bothe of well lerned and approued auctours, it ſhulde be redde thus: <hi>Clerici qui comam nutriunt, ab archidiacono, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſi noluerint tondiantur,</hi> Clerkes that let growe their buſſhes, ſhall be ſhorne of their archedecon, whether they wyll or not. And this appereth playnly to be the true redyng, bycauſe the interpreters ſaye, this ſentence was taken out of a law, made in the counſell of Agathenſe. And therin without doubte it is ſo written: <hi>Clerici qui comam nutriunt, ab archidiacono, etiam ſi noluerint, tondi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur.</hi> without any mention makyng of <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba</hi> the bearde.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the fourth counſell of Toletan, it
<pb facs="tcp:10933:17"/> was commaunded, that the doctours and chiefe prelates ſhoulde ſhaue all the vpper partis of their heedes, and to leaue on the nether parte a garland of heare aboue their eares: but as for the bearde they neuer thought theron.</p>
            <p>Alſo of the buſſhe onely, we fynde lyke commaundement in many placis, in rhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of auncient byſſhops, to gether with other thynges concernynge the lyfe of prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis: Finally Aniceius by the preceptes of the apoſtels, decreed, that the clergie ſhuld not nouryſhe theyr buſſhes: and ſurely he wold not haue paſſed ouer, without ſpekyng of the bearde, if he had eſtemed it a thynge vnhoneſt. For of truth to nouriſhe the buſhes is the facion of women, or els of ſuche men as lyue delicatly and vnchaſt. For the longe heared people were euer eſtemed both of the grekes and Latines for a token of foule luſt and fylthye lyuynge. Wherfore the lawes wyllynge religious men not onely to be with oute vycis, but alſo to eſchewe the occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſame, doo not withoute a cauſe forbydde theym to nouryſſhe theyr buſſhes. But ageyne on the other ſyde, hit beſemethe menne to haue longe beardes, for chiefely by that token (as I haue often ſayde) the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10933:17"/> vigorous ſtrengthe of manhode is decerned from the tendernes of women: ſo that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men oughte to nouryſſhe theyr buſſhes, and men theyr beardes. And for this cauſe the prieſtis were commaunded by the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſolemne counſel of Carthage, not to ſhaue theyr beardes, to the intent that they myght ſeme (lyke as they be) men, and ſhewe as it were a certayne maieſtie of their owne kynde, in theyr vtter apperaunce.</p>
            <p>But ye folowe the Rodians, whiche had a lawe amonge theym ageynſte ſhauynge: and yet commonly they were all ſhauen. Ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne alſo nowe to countrefeyte theym of Byſance, whoſe maners Chryſippus dydde mooſte hate for that ſame cauſe. For they dydde not onely make lawes ageynſte ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of berdes, but alſo ordeyned extreme punyſſhementes for the ſame, and yet the moſte parte of them, lyke as ye doo, loued to be ſhauen.</p>
            <p>Thus maye ye ſee, that in manye places, the frowardenes of yuelle people, diſtroye manye tymes the good maners. And lette no manne marueylle, thowghe falſe and corruptly wrytten bokes haue done moche harme by the ſpace of ſo many yeres paſte, ſoo that by the meanes of that erroure,
<pb facs="tcp:10933:18"/> many decrees, punyſhmentis of the proude and ſtubborne, and cruell chaſtiſinges haue bene brought vppe. O good lorde, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynges ſhall ye fynde in all olde bokes here and there moſte fautily redde? Howe many wordes chaunged? howe many cleane lefte out? howe many ſtryken oute? And I wolde to god, that there were fewer at this daye, whiche of theyr iniquitie doo peruerte many thynges.</p>
            <p>But beholde I beſeche you, what harmes ryſe by reaſon of depraued bokes. The ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Gelaſius the pope, in the xv. diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in our ſpirituall lawe is thus: <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis uiri Sedulij Paſcale opus, quod he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicis deſcripſit uerſibus, inſigni laude pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendum,</hi> The paſcall worke (ſayth he) of that honourable man Sedulius, whiche he wrote in heroicall verſis, is greattely to be preyſed: And yet hytherto ye ſhall fynd wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in bokes, that go commonly abrode, in the place of <hi>Heroicis uerſibus, hereticis uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus,</hi> whiche turneth the ſentence after this maner: The paſcal worke of that honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man Sedulins, whiche he wrote in erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious or hereticall verſis, is greattely to be preyſed. This one falſe worde brought ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a ſuſpicion to certayne men, which were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10933:18"/> true ꝓfeſſers of the lawes, that they thought all poetis verſis were erronious: and that they were nat worthye to be accompted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge good men, though they intreated of holy matters: whiche thynge we ſawe was alſo after ſuche a maner perſwaded to the pope Adrian the .vi. that he hated no kynde of peple worſe then poetes, thynkyng that no thyng that they dyd, was wel done. And yet to this day there be ſome diſcrete prelates ſo diſceyued with this falſe redynge, and with that other errour of ſhauing, that they thinke no man worthye to be a prieſt, that eyther maketh verſis, or weareth a bearde: ſuche a thynge it is ones to taſte an yuell opinion. But we ſhall lette paſſe to brynge in any mo exaumples, ſeinge we ſee dayly howe olde auctours haue ben corrupted by the meanes of falſe wryters. Nor I wolle not reherſe howe vngentilly the olde lawyers were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treted, by our lawyers that cam after them. For after theyr warkes were ones cutte in pieces by Tribunianus, and ſuch other bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, thei did not kepe theſe peces to gether, but ſuffred welnere euery vnlerned man to adde and minyſſhe at his pleaſure: and yet the ſame ſcrappis euyll and falſely recited, be taken for lawes, and they lack not a gret
<pb facs="tcp:10933:19"/> ſorte of defenders.</p>
            <p>Thus many thynges are dayly brought to lyght, whiche gyue vs warnynge of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of our forefathers, wherin they haue bene ouerſene this many yeres, or deceyued by the falſenes of bokes. Wherfore it is the leſſe meruayle, if the decree of the counſell of Carthage, be founde nowe otherwyſe wrytten, than it was put forth in tyme paſt.</p>
            <p>Well go to, we haue ſette here a ſure fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for oure defence: A lawe is recyted, whiche we haue playnely proued no lawe. Nother berdes ar not forbydden by the law of exaumples. It is alſo proued, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemeth euery good and honeſt man to weare a bearde. Neuertheleſſe they brynge forthe one reaſon to make them ſeme Romaynes, and yet they intende to folowe the delycate maners of the Sicilians. Many of them ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, that beardis were diſanulled by the popes of Rome, bycauſe the Grekes vſed to weare them: For they ſey it is not leful for a prieſt of the Romaynes to folowe theym in habyte &amp; maners, that haue forſaken the churche of Rome. Therfore we muſte ſhaue our berdes, except we wol be heretikes or re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>belles. To this what other anſwere ſhall I make, but that our accuſers be perauenture
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10933:19"/> good men (I wol not call them inuious, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landyſhe, nor vnlerned) but may happe more ſimple than good men ſhuld be: which thinke that beardes ſhulde be deſpiſed of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, and that the people be accurſte that weareth them, and alſo they thynke, where ſo euer they be, they make the place vnholye and voyde of all good lucke, bycauſe the grekes wol not obey to theyr conſtitutions, I maruayle from whenſe they gatte theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, whiche howe foolyſſhe and howe chyldyſſhe they be, euery manne perceyueth. For if they wyl affirm it to be done bycauſe of the grekes: I beſeche you lette them tell me to what Italian it hathe doone good, or what hathe the pope gotten by it, when the ſame diſcorde hath ben the cauſe of ſo many euyls, whiche yet abhorreth any man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre.</p>
            <p>I wolde to God oure forefathers hadde not benne ſo wylfulle and fulle of ſtryfe, ſomme beynge to extreme in kepynge of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ceremonyes and lawes, whiche were but of ſmalle effecte, ſomme in makynge of newe, ſomme in breakynge and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge of olde cuſtomes and maners, the whyche hadde benne kepte manye yeres.</p>
            <p>(I ſpeake onely of cuſtomes, bycauſe thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:10933:20"/> thynges that perteyne to the feythe, are of an other kynde) but yf ſuch buſynes had not bene, we hadde not loſte ſo manye ſortis of people, nor ſo many realmes. The greekes had not forſaken vs, we hadde kepte ſtylle the Ile of Aegei, we had not loſte Thracia, we had nat loſte the realme of Byzance, we had nat loſt all Aſia, nother Hieruſalem had nat ben inhabyted with infidels, ſo greattely to oure diſhonour, ye and to ſpeake of later tyme, for ſuch cauſes Boeme and Germanie ſhulde not haue ſette ſo lyght by the pope. For in gouernynge many tymes ſome inciden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis happen, whiche are of ſo ſmalle weyght, that they maye be eaſily eyther graunted or els ſuffered: the whiche thynges if they be ſtubbornely denied, they cauſe indignation amonge the vnlerned people: And ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indignation cometh chauffynge and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouryng, after chauffyng daily increaſing of malice, &amp; ſhortly after malice cruel enmities, and than mortall warre. Whan our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers commaunded the Romayne prieſtis, to ſhaue theyr beardes, in diſpite of the grekes, to the intent there myght be a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Romaynes and them: they cauſed the Grekes to be ſo vexed with that ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſention, that they bare euen as greate &amp; lyke
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10933:20"/> malice ageynſte vs than, as they dydde atte the tyme, whan they hauyng warre amonge them ſelfe, were of ſo miſcheuous a mynde, that they hadde leuer make a leage with the Turkes, and ſeke the felowſhyppe of them, than to aſke helpe of vs, or receyue our aide, whan it was wyllyngly offred. And ſo they were deceyued, and by the fals fayth of their ennemies betrayed, and vtterly diſtroyed.</p>
            <p>They loſte theyr kyngdome, theyr countrey was ſpoyled, theyr aulters were robbed, made vnholy, and lefte deſolate: and by and by we were broughte in the ſame perylle by the meanes of theyr chaunce. To the which people if that thynge had bene granted, that was of none effect, the name of chriſtendom had ben ſpredde abrode bothe far and wide: neyther that ſame coote of our lord, that had no ſeame, had bene rent in ſo many peces as we ſe it nowe adayes.</p>
            <p>But what nede we to make mention of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens damages and fautis, whanne we may ſe, as touchyng berdes, ſuche variances at home at our doores, that it hath broughte vp a perpetuall ſclaunder to the hygh order of preeſthode. In continuance of tyme the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lites of our forefathers came ſo farre forth, that by the meanes of ſhauynge, the people<pb facs="tcp:10933:21"/> was ſo diſguiſed, that men and women were ſcant knowen a ſonder: And by this it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened (if the tale be trewe that is in enerye mans mouth) that a woman was choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pope of Rome, to the perpetuall rebuke of that ſame holy order. In remembraunce of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dede, the Romaynes to this daye ſhewe the place, poyntynge with a fynger, where that ſame high woman prieſte, beinge in the popes ſtede, dyd trauayle of a chylde. And leeſte ſuche an other chaunce myght happen, many men beleue, that euer after it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned by a lawe, that the ſame foly of oure forefathers ſhulde be openly declared at the ſtallyng of euery newe pope. For at the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit of ſaynt Iohn, where is gethered to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on that ſolemne feaſte day, a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people, of all maner of nations: the newe Poope is there conſtreyned, in the ſyght of them all, to proue hym ſelfe a man by many ſufficient wytneſſes. And whan the thyng is ones pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by the voyce of the crier, by and by it is ſhewed aboute in euery place: and than we beleue ſurely, we haue a laufull man to our pope, when it myghte be euidently knowen, we had him that we ought to haue, without any ſuch wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derment. Theſe I ſay be the thynges, whiche haue comen vp
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10933:21"/> in tyme paſt by the ſmothnes and delycatnes of ſhauynge, where on the other part it was neuer founde, that any ſuche inconuenience came by the meanes of beardes. If the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of prieſtis are to be corrected or loked nere vpon, it is beſte to take hede, that they, whiche are choſen to that honeſte dignitie to be miniſters to god almightye, ſhulde not be defyled with vile occupations or offices. Let them kepe no vittaylynge houſes, let them be no maryners, lette them weare no longe daggers, or ſuche other weapons, let them weave none armour nor pied garmentis, let theym not falle to quaftynge or to dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, finally let them forbeare al ſuche thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whiche do ſhewe lyghtnes, folyſhenes, or vnclenlynes. Truely if our accuſers had taken hede to theſe thynges, they hadde not ben ſo lyttell regarded of euery man as they be. But when they deuiſe with ſo great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to condemne their berdes whiche doth increce their dignite, they do not only deſerue to be diſpreiſed, but alſo they brynge them ſelfe in to ſclaunder of waywardeneſſe and ſuperſtition. I ſpeake this for no malyce, but hit greuethe me to ſee ſomme menne, verye excellente otherwayes bothe in ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and perfectneſſe of lyuynge (excepte
<pb facs="tcp:10933:22"/> I ſhulde belye them, whiche beinge deceyuid by ſome fooles, what ſo euer they be, vnder the colour of goodnes, fal into ſuche conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and be ſo erneſt for ſo lyght cauſes, ye (yf I myght ſpeake it) very foolyſhe trifles, and when there be many hygher matters to be loked vpon, to exercyſe theyr ſtudye, and to labour to put downe berdes, which hurte nother god nor manne: nor yet there is anye cauſe why they ſhulde go aboute to defende their oppinion by certayne newe prouinciall lawes, the whiche thoughe they were neuer ſo firmely ſtrengthed by man, ye althoughe the pope agreed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym ſelfe, yet if there be founde a truer reaſon, they be bothe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, corrected, and changed. For the lawes, the decrees, and inſtitutions, for cauſe made, as the nede of matters requireth, and as the tyme aſketh, the pope by the counſayle of his bretherne, and of his hyghe power, dothe daily correcte, for do, ordeyne, and ſtablyſhe: and theſe thynges that they agree vpon, or he alone, be taken for lawes. And it is moſte firmely prouided by precepte of the hygh ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the lawes, that euery laſte lawe ſhall wype away the fyrſte.</p>
            <p>But what more euident or more holy lawe ſhall we ſeeke, for the wearynge of beardes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10933:22"/> than that ſame, whiche the hyghe byſſhoppe Iulius the ſeconde, and Clement the .vii. did ſhew in theyr tyme, by theyr owne examples gyuynge? It pleaſed Iulius longe tyme to weare a bearde, It pleaſed Clement alſo to weare a bearde, It pleaſed the holy college of Cardinalles to doo the ſame, It pleaſed both the other prelates and poore prieſtis in lyke wyſe: And ſhall we tarie to loke out an other counſayle, when in dede there is none ſuche at all? Or ſhall we deuyſe to renewe weake lawes, or thoſe that be nowe worne out: when this ſame liuely lawe is to this daye euery where in ſtrengthe, euery where obſerued, louyngely receyued, and putte in vſe in euerye place, for a lawe made and approued?</p>
            <p>Amonge the Venetians, the Piſans, the Brutians, the Calabers, the Sicilians, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them of Champayne, amonge the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayne, the Etruſcians, and many other peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Italie, where as eche citie is inſtituted with right laudable lawes and moſte honeſt maners, it is eſtemed and taken for a verye greatte offence, to kyſſe an other mans wyfe or his doughter. And yet in the chiefe parte of the ſame region, and betwene the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of Pady and Doria, and from thenſe
<pb facs="tcp:10933:23"/> by all the mountaynes of Allobroges, and in euery citie, that is moſte populouſly inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byted with frenche menne, and villages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Pyren and Reynes, from the eaſte par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis to the greatte occean ſee, the ſame licence of kyſſynge is ſo moche ſuffred, that whan ſo euer thou ſhalte come to the howſe of thin ooſte, or of thy frende, excepte thou fyrſt of all kyſſe his wyfe, his daughters, and al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther women in the howſe, and beclyp theym in thyne armes, thou ſhalte be iudged chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe, or proude, or els to be theyr ennemie. And ſo that, that among vs here is thought to be a ſhamefulle thynge, is taken amonge them for a great gentylnes and a familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Of ſuche weight is the cuſtome and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of people of longe tyme vſed. Alſo in ſome cities and countreyes, ſome thynges not ſo honeſte, are yet by reaſon of cuſtome and vſe, and longe and ſure conſente of the people, growen into a lawe. And thynke ye than to take away this ſame venerable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, of grauitie and ſadnes, that hath bene receyued and allowed both by the examples of the high byſhoppes, and alſo by the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of al the people? Neyther ye remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre not the ſayenge of the moſt wiſe prince, beinge daylye proued afore your eyes: <hi>Eos
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10933:23"/> qui aliter uiuere uolunt, quam ſe habeant mores eorum, inter quos uiuunt, ſuſpicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos, aut intemperantes haberi,</hi> They that lyue after an other ſorte, then the cuſtome is of the people and countreye, where they dwelle, are taken for ſuſpicious and vnruly perſones. And if ye thynke it beſt to ſtycke to one lawe, what ſo euer it be, whether it be weake, corrupte, or of ſmall effecte: doo ye not ſee the mooſte ſadde ſentences of men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſte you, whiche haue the high auctoritie bothe to interprete and to make the lawes? For they, whiche by their high power haue made lawes to all the worlde, what lawes they haue made of prieſtis beardes, it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more playnely by theym ſelfe, thanne thoughe they hadde grauen it in a table of braſſe. But admytte it be an offence: graunt alſo (though it appere not) that Alexander the thyrde, was of the ſame mynde, as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bokes do ſhewe. More ouer, graunte it to be eſtemed a lothly dede: and that a prieſt with a bearde ought nat to meddell with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the holy ſacramentis, nor be in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany among me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but (after your iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) to be exiled or kept in perpetuall priſon. Wel go to, let your oratours begyn to accuſe vs, let them do theyr vttermoſte, lette them ley to our charges what ſo euer they can before
<pb facs="tcp:10933:24"/> the iudges, let them make vs to forfayt our goodes, and lyke as rebels &amp; murderers ar wonte to be handled, let them mynde to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate vs. But where? Where ſhal the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be? Before whom ſhal they plede their cauſe? Who ſhall aknowledge this to be an offence? Who ſhall condempne vs? I wolle haue them go to thoſe that be moſte ſadde &amp; beſt aduiſed, and vnto them, to whoſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and determinations not onely al the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon people, but alſo men of gret reputation and might wyl ſtande. This is the iugement of the twelue men, whiche are ordeyned to ſytte in the biſhops palaice, to gyue ſentence vpon matters in debate: Of the whiche ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner there were ſome tyme certayne menne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Grekes (when they flouryſſhed) called <hi>Amphictyones,</hi> whiche concerninge the lawes, did make anſwere to al maner of people. And theſe (I ſeye) be the iudges, whiche we had nede to haue to make an ende of our matter. Therfore beholde vs here re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy at hande, we neither rebelle ageynſt you, nor we are not about to flee, we be contente to abyde the iudgement, ye ſhall not nede to attache vs, and kepe vs in holde. Begyn ye nowe to call for iudgement. Beholde here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eies a holle college of choſen men,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10933:24"/> of good lyfe, and well ſkylled in the lawes. Whervppon do ye tarie? For what cauſe are ye ſo abaſhed? Me thynketh your anſweres be very farre to ſeke. Where is nowe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of your accuſation? that horrible wounder, that prieſtes ſhuld weare beardis, whiche ye ſaye is a newe crime, that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer harde of before this tyme? Verily ye maye nowe perceyue youre owne folye, and what tryfils ye haue gethered to gether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the thornes. For ye can fynde no iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but they gyue ſentence ageynſt you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye begynne to ſpeake, excepte your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes wolde be bothe iudges and accuſers.</p>
            <p>Do ye not ſee, if ye ſtryue ageynſt beardes, there be ſo many good men that weare ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that your buſynes ſhall be laughed to ſcorne with euery man? Neither there is any cauſe why, that you being but thre in nombre or foure at the moſte, ſhulde thynke to haue the true knowlege. This is your wyl, &amp; not your iugement: &amp; where as al men thoughte before, that it was but an errour in you for lacke of knowlege, nowe ſeinge ye ſtycke ſtyl in your opinion, the truth apperyng ſo plein afore your face, euery man maye knowe, ye do it not of ignorance, but of a very proude and obſtinate mynde, leſt your euyl meninge
<pb facs="tcp:10933:25"/> ſhoulde be perceyued. Stynte ye therfore nowe to make any further buſyneſſe, and thoſe maners of men, whiche ye ſe are mete to be vſed, allowe ye them alſo, or els if you be ſo tender and delycate, that ye can not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde to be ſene lyke men, yet be contente at the leeſte waye, that other men vſe them ſelfe as they ſhulde do.</p>
            <p>Thus yf ye intende to determyne youre matter, by the lawes, ye ſee to what paſſe it wyll comme. If ye grounde you vpon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, ye can fynde no ſuche honeſtie in ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge of a mans face. If ye wolle ſpeake of cuſtome and maners: the ſame cuſtome to weare a bearde is ſo vſed with princis and chiefe reulers, that nowe it maye be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a lawe.</p>
            <p>Behold I beſeche you the ancient doctours of our Senate howſe, whiche are men ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in all mener ſciences, whiche are not wonte to do any thynge out of good order: ye ſe them weare beardes, which thyng they wolde not do, excepte they thought it mete for a prieſte, &amp; for euer honeſt man. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion amonge all theſe excellent men, thou ſhalte fynde very fewe without beardes. And thoſe few, if thou woldeſt demaund for what cauſe they were no beardes, they woll
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10933:25"/> make many other excuſes, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſei, it is vnſemely for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of holy orders, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge to preferre the truth before their own maners. What ſhuld I here reherce any mo exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of other holy men, as archbyſhops and byſſhoppes, that haue worne beardes, whiche wolde not haue worne them, excepte they had knowen very wel, it was not repug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant to the lawes of Chriſt? &amp; ſhal any man be ſo bolde to recite other lawes before their examples? when it is openly knowen, that they wold not vſe a thynge, which was not a patron of perfecte religion and honeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Me thynketh our accuſers ſhuld nowe waxe wery, to iuge that thing yuel, which by the conſent of al good men is allowed to be bothe ſemely and laudable. Furthermore where they recyte a lawe for theyr parte, it appereth there is no ſuche: but (as I haue ſayde) by falſe wrytynge, that taken for a lawe, that neuer was ſo ordeyned: if it were let theym vnderſtande, that by the examples of the two hygh byſhops, Iulius &amp; Clement, it is clene abrogate &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nulled. If any man wol ſey, that they myght not breke it, than let him deny al the lawes made by them. What ſhal I ſey to theſe felowes, which wol beleue nothyng but theyr owne fantaſies, to theym
<pb facs="tcp:10933:26"/> there is nothynge harde within an olyue, nor without a nutte. For yf there be any aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie gyuen to princis and to general counſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, prieſtis ought to weare beardes.</p>
            <p>More ouer if they had not iudged it ſemely for a religious man, they wold neuer haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded that prieſtes ſhuld be vnſhauen, nor they wolde neuer haue ſuffered theyr owne facis to be pictured with beardes.</p>
            <p>The picture of Iulius is made with a berde in the ſyght of all men, The face of Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is dayly coyned with a bearde bothe in gold and ſyluer. But thoſe men (whiche ſo cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vexe vs) whan they condempne beardes, they vnderſtonde not, that they blame the hyghe byſſhoppe, prelates, and other ſadde men, and that they mocke the conſtitutions of holy men: they damne Peter and Paule, and all the appoſtels, ye and they ley immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie to Chriſte hym ſelfe. There is no man more vniuſte then he, whiche thynketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge welle doone, but that that he dothe hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But for what intent do they make all this buſynes? For what cauſe go they ſo buſily about to moue and put away all berded men from miniſtrynge of the ſacramentis, from the churche, &amp; from all mens companyes? I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10933:26"/> can not diuiſe what they ſhaulde meane, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte they wolde haue ſeynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptyſte, ſeynt Iamis, and ſeynt Ierom, with many other banyſhed out of heuen. For it apperith by our aduerſaries iudgemente, that thoſe were frowarde perſons, rebels, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of good maners. For what other thing by theyr interpretation, maketh they hym, that weareth a bearde, but a proude and an yuell man, that lyueth not after the lawes? and he is wycked, that deſerueth to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed out of the churche of Chriſte. O tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> howe myſerable and vnhappy were all theſe holye men before named, to choſe a lyfe ſo peynfull and laborous, as to forſake al the pleaſures of this worlde, and to liue in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, to make theyr bodyes leane with faſtynge, watchynge, and prayenge: if they ſhoulde onely for theyr beardes be iudged before god for yuell lyuers. Who doubteth, if they, whiche nowe weare beardes, ſhall be iudged for yuell lyuers, but that thoſe holy men before ſayde, and other that haue ben auctours of that facion, ſhalbe lyke wiſe accuſed of our aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>If we demaunde of our accuſers, what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection they haue to be made ſo ſmoth: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubte they wyll anſwere and ſeye, it is
<pb facs="tcp:10933:27"/> done bycauſe the heares ſhuld not be dypped in the mooſte holye bloudde of Chriſte: And they ſey, and it is very trouth, that al honor and reuerence ought to be done to this moſte bleſſed ſacrament. But I beſeche you than, is there any thynge the leſſe reuerence done to this moſte hygh ſacrament, if the miniſter ſhewe hym ſelfe (as Alexis ſayth) more like a man than a woman? For Alexis ſaythe, that God is not offended with heares, the whiche ſerue to expreſſe the perfecte ſtate of man. I beſeche you, be heares ſo fylthy, and ſo greatlye to be deſpiſed, that they are not worthy to come nere the bleſſed ſacrament? But foule nayles, ſcabby fyngers, a fylthy face, with all the reſte of the bodye beſyde may do it none vnreuerence: &amp; thynke thoſe men then, that a bearde is ſo fylthy a thinge, and ſo hateful to god, that it may in no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wyſe comme nere the bleſſed ſacrament? And yet for all this, the ſelfe ſame thynge, the whiche they commaunde ſo holily to be done, they doo hit not theym ſelfes. For whiche of all theſe holy menne (I woll not calle them diſſemblers) ſhall you fynde, that is ſhauen euery day, as the prieſtes of Egipt be? And excepte they do ſhaue their berdes euery day, or els ones for al, plucke out the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10933:27"/> heares by the rootes, they are not able to perfourme theyr ſayenge. For within a daye after, or two at the moſte, when they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre ageyne, they contaminate the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with heares, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte the ſame offence, for whiche they accuſed them that weare berades. They woll ſey, that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clennes of the heares, that haue growen but a day or a weke is not lyke to that that hath growen a moneth, a yere, or longer tyme: as who wolde ſaye, it were none offence for a man to breke the faſtynge day with a calfe of a weke or a moneth olde, but he that ſhuld eate a great oxe dyd greuouſly offende. And ſo our moſte diſcrete accuſers woll ſeye, that the moſte bleſſed ſacramente is not offended with a heer of one day or a week is growing, but he that touchethe it with a longe heare, that hath growen a moneth, or a holle yere, doth vnreuerently vſe it. Trewely this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is of ſo ſmalle effecte, and ſo vntrue, that it is not worthye to be taried any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vppon.</p>
            <p>Therfore lette vs paſſe ouer this, and we that be menne, lette vs kepe with al dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the ſame ſobre and honeſte cuſtome of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſeing it can be proued by no reaſon, why a bearde ſhuld be diſpiſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:28"/>
            <p>On the other parte ſmothynge and ſhauing (as I haue ſayde alwayes) whether it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a man by nature, or by handy craft, it dothe ſhewe an outward apparence of ſynne, and wyckednes, or els of other thinges, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are not worthy to be preyſed.</p>
            <p>Yet bycauſe they wolde haue ſomewhat more to babble vppon, they ſey, it beſemeth not a prieſte to profeſſe by his habyte, a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, or a heuy mynde. Beholde theſe va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyant defenders of our chriſten religion. Be holde the grauitie and wyſedome of thoſe, whiche wolde take vppon them to be other mennes gydes, they wolde haue prieſtis to ſhewe in their out warde ſemblance none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge but myrth and lyghtenes, as it were a ſcoffer (ye if I mought ſey the truth) euen lyke a baudy ieſter. Well let vs graunt to that. Admytte that a berde is a token of ſorow &amp; heuynes: meane ye than, that priſtis ſhoulde neyther mourne, nor be troubled in theyr myndes, nor yet lyue after their owne pleaſure? O ſtony hartis, O cruel myndes, of the whiche ſorte there was neuer none harde of before. Oughte not prieſtes moſte of all to mourne in this myſerable worlde, when there is no man that hath any cauſe to laughe? We are conſtreyned by Nature to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10933:28"/> mourne for the loſſe of euerye dere beloued thyng. There is no man except he be madde, that woll forbydde the mother to mourne at the buryenge of her chylde. And wold theſe delycate felowes of the court of Rome, lette and forbydde vs to wepe and wayle in oure owne funerals? Woll they forbydde vs to mourne and make ſorowe, to beholde howe all Italie is ouerronne and diſtroyed, to ſee the noble citie of Rome ſubdued, ſpoyled, and robbed, and the inhabitantis therof murdred and ſlayne, to ſee the great vexation of all chriſtendome, and in the drede and feare of ſo many folde great peryls, and finally in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdynge the confuſion of the holle worlde, wol they warne vs to be heuy and ſorowful? And as moche of Italy as remayneth, lyeth reked vp in the aſſhes of her burnyng: and no parte therof is more conſumed by fire, than that that longed to prieſtis. Vnder the aſhes lyen the hotte glowyng cooles, whiche ſeme to kendell vp a farre greatter fyre (ere it be ought longe) than is paſſed. And is it not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs, at leeſt wyſe to ſhew a mourning chiere, and with a heuy countenaunce to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our great drede, and myſerable fortune? And we beinge forſaken of ſo many chriſten princis, and mooſte vnworthyly reputed, by
<pb facs="tcp:10933:29"/> whoſe counſeyle and ſufferaunce, we were caſte out as a common praye, and all taken, as many as were at Rome, and ſpoyled of all our goodes that we hadde, and are beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde with intollerable tributis, and we ſuffre and endure great crueltie, iniurie, and many folde miſeries, and we be not yet lyke to ſee an ende of theſe great calamities: for not onely our foes, but alſo our frendes do dayly catche from vs what ſo euer they can, and they ſpare nat ſo moche as perteyne to the houſes of religion. And yet our accuſers in this vnlucky and moſte myſerable tyme, in ſo great darkenes of the common weale, in ſo great perturbation of all thynges, goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to forbydde vs, with feare of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, that we in no wyſe ſhulde lament our vnluckynes of mooſte wretched chaunce.</p>
            <p>All the worlde gapethe to deuoure Italye: They haue ſucked it as nere as they can, and thoſe ſcrappes that remayne, they intende to ſwype cleane awaye.</p>
            <p>And theſe, our ydell accuſers take thought for nothynge, but gyue theym ſelfes onelye to ſlouthe, and they prepare to lyue in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte and eaſe, in luſte and in lykynge, and goo aboute to ſhaue and to make ſmothe theyr facis, lyke as thowghe thereby they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10933:29"/> ſhulde greattely helpe and ſuccour the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welthe of chriſtendome, whiche is now in greatte ieoperdye and ruyne. And they thynke they haue ſufficientely prouyded for vs, if they can perſwade vs to forſake oure mannely ſtate, and to ſhewe our ſelfes lyke women. But I woll bydde them fare well, and as men vnworthy of honeſt companye, to be ſent away ſomewhyther, where they may remayne vnknowen, and lye and inioye theyr fonde appetite. We wolle iudge theym worthy of none other punyſſhement, nor we woll neyther enuye theyr quietnes, nor yet hate theym, for that they be ſo delycate to them ſelfe, in caſe that they dare not, nor be not able, to hurte or hynder the maners of menne, that haue bene welle and diſcretely ordeyned.</p>
            <p>But wherto ſhulde I ſtryue or reaſon any further with you ageynſte the ſmothenes of ſhauynge, ſeinge it hathe ben proued to you bothe by the inſtitutions and holy preceptis of oure forefathers in olde tyme, that we ought to let our beardes growe, to thintent we maye folowe the exaumple of Chriſte &amp; his diſciples, and of ſo many other fathers that ledde a perfecte good lyfe, and to the intente we moughte eſchewe and aduoyde
<pb facs="tcp:10933:30"/> the occaſions of reprofe and ſclaunder, and to fle the ſuſpicion and detraction of delycat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and laſte of all to the intent we mought be iuged rather men than women? For what cauſe ſhulde we be aſhamed of our beardes, if it be well ſhewed, what a bearde is, and howe well it becometh a ſadde and an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If it be wel proued, how gretly a berd in creſeth the dignitie of a priſt? Why ſhuld we be aſſhamed of a bearde, if we fynde that by the lawe of nature, it is neceſſary, and by the lawe wrytten, acceptable to god, and by the lawe of grace it is no where diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. If the errour of them be ouercome, that holde the contrary opinion: If alſo the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the bleſſed ſacrament ſhuld be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with heres, be wyped awey, and that it is well proued, that a bearde doth none of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the reuerence of that moſte high di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine miſterie: If the high princis of our chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten religion haue made a lawe ageynſte ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, whiche as appereth by their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples they wolde we ſhuld folowe: If v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame lawe there hath folowed not a ſecrete, nor a darke, but an open and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſente of the people, ye and welnere of all maner of nations, which euery where are ſene to ſtande ſtyffely in that oppinion:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10933:30"/> Wherfore then, I beſeche you, ſhuld not we ſtycke and leane to reaſon rather then to abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion? and rather folowe the examples of ſo many vertuous and noble men, than cleaue to the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a few ſuperſtitious perſons? If the iudgement of this matter were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttted to me, I wolde gyue a perpetualle ſentence, that from heneforthe no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge profeſſed into holy orders, ſhulde ſhaue his bearde, accordynge to the vſe of thoſe holy fathers: whiche knowynge it a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thynge to god, made ſuch vowes, when they intended moſte to be reconciled ageyne to hym. Or elles I feare me, we ſhall ones ageyne prouoke the yre of god ageynſte vs, who beinge diſpleaſed with ſuche feminine delycatenes (as ſhauynge and ſmothynge of our ſkynnes, and makynge ſofte our lyppes, and perfumynge, and ſuche other) we maye very well beleue, he dydde ſende al kyndes of miſchefe into the towne of Rome, whiche yet hytherto we fele: And therfore he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded our goodes to be taken frome vs, and our ſumptuous houſes to be eyther ouer throwen or els burned, and many other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes of our wanton myndes to be plucked awey from vs.</p>
            <p>But when he ſhall ſe vs retourne to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:10933:31"/> mynde, and that we cal to remembrance, that we be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and entred into holy orders, and that we wol chaſtiſe our luſt &amp; lyking, &amp; ſet naught by delectations and pleaſures of this worlde, and clene forſake our ſofte and feminate affections, &amp; wytnes by our berdis, that we intende to leade a more conſtant and manly lyfe: without doute he wol metigate his diſpleaſure, and begyn to turne theſe bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and cruell chaſtiſinges into a more eaſye and more gentyl punyſhment, and at the laſt graunt vs an ende of our calamities and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, that haue ſo longe continued. But in caſe we wol begyn to vſe ageyne our olde fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of delicate and ſynfull liuing, I am ſore aferde, leſt that he being more angry, &amp; more diſpleſed towarde vs, than euer he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, woll ſende ſo ſharpe punyſſhement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs, that it wyll lyttell auayle vs, to pray him of pitie: and that he wol withdraw aweye from vs his grace, and ſuffre vs to ſlyde into all calamities, and ſo, (whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god defende) the vniuerſall furye of al the world, beinge ſtered vp to crueltie, he ſhal turne into our miſchefe, ſo that in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what by the menes of our wicked liuing and the vngentyl dealyng of the people, we ſhalbe vtterly diſtroyed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10933:31"/>
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS THO. BERTHELETI. M.D.XXXIII. CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
